<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="persistence">
  <title>Seam Persistence Reference</title>

   <para>
      Seam provides extensive support for the two most popular persistence
      architectures for Java: Hibernate3, and the Java Persistence API
      introduced with EJB 3.0. Seam's unique state-management architecture
      allows the most sophisticated ORM integration of any web application 
      framework.
   </para>
    
   <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
    
      <para>
         Seam grew out of the frustration of the Hibernate team with the 
         statelessness typical of the previous generation of Java application 
         architectures. The state management architecture of Seam was originally
         designed to solve problems relating to persistence &#8212; in particular
         problems associated with <emphasis>optimistic transaction processing</emphasis>.
         Scalable online applications always use optimistic transactions. An atomic 
         (database/JTA) level transaction should not span a user interaction unless
         the application is designed to support only a very small number of concurrent
         clients. But almost all interesting work involves first displaying data
         to a user, and then, slightly later, updating the same data. So Hibernate was
         designed to support the idea of a persistence context which spanned an
         optimistic transaction. 
      </para>
       
      <para>
           Unfortunately, the so-called "stateless" architectures that preceded Seam and 
           EJB 3.0 had no construct for representing an optimistic transaction. So, instead,
           these architectures provided persistence contexts scoped to the atomic
           transaction. Of course, this resulted in many problems for users, and is the
           cause of the number one user complaint about Hibernate: the dreaded 
           <literal>LazyInitializationException</literal>. What we need is a construct
           for representing an optimistic transaction in the application tier.
      </para>
       
      <para>
         EJB 3.0 recognizes this problem, and introduces the idea of a stateful
         component (a stateful session bean) with an <emphasis>extended persistence 
         context</emphasis> scoped to the lifetime of the component. This is a
         partial solution to the problem (and is a useful construct in and of 
         itself) however there are two problems:
      </para>
       
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
              <para>
                  The lifecycle of the stateful session bean must be managed manually
                  via code in the web tier (it turns out that this is a subtle problem
                  and much more difficult in practice than it sounds).
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
              <para>
                  Propagation of the persistence context between stateful components
                  in the same optimistic transaction is possible, but tricky.
              </para>
          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>
          Seam solves the first problem by providing conversations, and stateful
          session bean components scoped to the conversation. (Most conversations 
          actually represent optimistic transactions in the data layer.) This is
          sufficient for many simple applications (such as the Seam booking
          demo) where persistence context propagation is not needed. For more
          complex applications, with many loosly-interacting components in each
          conversation, propagation of the persistence context across components
          becomes an important issue. So Seam extends the persistence context
          management model of EJB 3.0, to provide conversation-scoped extended
          persistence contexts.
      </para>
    
   </section>
   
   <section>
      <title>Getting Started</title>
      
      <para>
         To get started with Seam persistence you need to add the
         <literal>seam-persistence.jar </literal> and the 
         <literal>weld-extensions.jar</literal> to you deployment. If you are in
         a java SE environment you will probably also require 
         <literal>seam-xml.jar</literal> as well for configuration purposes. The
         relevant maven configuration is as follows:
      </para>
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.seam.persistence</groupId>
  <artifactId>seam-persistence-api</artifactId>
  <version>${seam.persistence.version}</version>
</dependency>

<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.seam.persistence</groupId>
  <artifactId>seam-persistence-impl</artifactId>
  <version>${seam.persistence.version}</version>
</dependency>

<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.weld</groupId>
  <artifactId>weld-extensions</artifactId>
  <version>${weld.extensions.version}</version>
</dependency>

<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.seam.xml</groupId>
  <artifactId>seam-xml-config</artifactId>
  <version>${seam.xml.version}</version>
</dependency>  
]]></programlisting>  
      
      <para>
         You will also need to have a JPA provider on the classpath. If you are
         using java EE this is taken care of for you. If not, we recommend hibernate.
      </para>

<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupId>org.hibernate</groupId>
  <artifactId>hibernate-core</artifactId>
  <version>3.5.1-Final</version>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>      
   </section>
   
   <section id="persistence.transactions" >
      <title>Transaction Management</title>
      
      <para>
         Unlike EJB session beans CDI beans are not transactional by default. Seam 
         brings declarative transaction management to CDI beans by enabling them to
         use <code>@TransactionAttribute</code>. Seam also provides the 
         <code>@Transactional</code> annotation, for environments where java EE
         APIs are not present. 
      </para>
      <section>
         <title>Configuration</title>
         <para>
            In order to enable declarative transaction management for managed beans 
            you need to list the transaction interceptor in beans.xml:
         </para>
         <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<beans xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="
      http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee 
      http://docs.jboss.org/cdi/beans_1_0.xsd">
   <interceptors>
      <class>org.jboss.seam.persistence.transaction.TransactionInterceptor</class>
   </interceptors>
</beans>]]></programlisting>         
         <para>
            If you are in a Java EE 6 environment then you are good to go, 
            no additional configuration is required. 
         </para>
         <para>
            If you are not in an EE environment you may need to configure some
            things with seam-xml. You may need the following entries in your
            beans.xml file:
         </para>
         <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<beans xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xmlns:s="urn:java:ee" 
   xmlns:t="urn:java:org.jboss.seam.persistence.transaction"
   xsi:schemaLocation="
      http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee 
      http://docs.jboss.org/cdi/beans_1_0.xsd">

      <t:SeSynchronizations>
         <s:modifies/>
      </t:SeSynchronizations>

      <t:EntityTransaction>
         <s:modifies />         
      </t:EntityTransaction>
      
</beans>]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            Lets look at these individually.
         </para>
         
         <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<t:SeSynchronizations>
  <s:modifies/>
</t:SeSynchronizations>]]></programlisting>
         
         <para>
            Seam will attempt to use JTA synchronizations if possible. If not then you need to install the
            <code>SeSynchronzations</code> bean to allow seam to handle synchronizations manually. 
            Synchronizations allow seam to respond to transaction events such as 
            <literal>beforeCompletion()</literal> and <literal>afterCompletion()</literal>, and are needed
            for the proper operation of the 
            <link linkend="persistence.seam-managed-persistence-contexts">Seam Managed Persistence Context</link>.
         </para>  

         <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<t:EntityTransaction>
   <s:modifies />         
</t:EntityTransaction>]]></programlisting>         
         
         <para>
            By default seam will attempt to look up <literal>java:comp/UserTransaction</literal> from JNDI 
            (or alternatively retrieve it from the EJBContext if a container managed transaction is active).
            Installing <code>EntityTransaction</code> tells seam to use the JPA <code>EntityTransaction</code>
            instead. To use this you must have a 
            <link linkend="persistence.seam-managed-persistence-contexts">Seam Managed Persistence Context</link>
            installed with qualifier <code>@Default</code>. 
         </para>       
         <para>
            TODO: document how to use different qualifiers.
         </para>
         <note>
            <para>
               You should avoid <code>EntityTransaction</code> if you have more than one persistence unit in your
               application. Seam does not support installing multiple <code>EntityTransaction</code> beans, and
               the <code>EntityTransaction</code> interface does not support two phase commit, so unless you are
               careful you may have data consistency issues. If you need multiple persistence units in your 
               application then we highly recommend using an EE 6 compatible server, such as Jboss 6. 
            </para>
         </note>
      
      </section>
      
      <section>
         <title>Declarative Transaction Management</title>
                  
         <para>
            Seam adds declarative transaction support to managed beans. Seam re-uses the EJB
            <code>@TransactionAttribute</code> for this purpose, however it also provides 
            an alternative <code>@Transactional</code> annotation for environments where 
            the EJB API's are not available. An alternative to <code>@ApplicationException</code>, 
            <code>@SeamApplicationException</code> is also provided. Unlike EJBs managed beans
            are not transactional by default, you can change this by adding the
            <code>@TransactionAttribute</code> to the bean class. 
         </para>
         
         <para>
            If you are using seam managed transactions you do not need to worry about declarative
            transaction management. Seam will automatically start a transaction for you at the 
            start of the faces request, and commit it before the render response phase.
         </para>
         
         <warning>
            <para>
               <code>@SeamApplicationException</code> will not control transaction rollback 
               when using EJB container managed transactions. If you are in an EE environment 
               then you should always use the EJB API's, namely <code>@TransactionAttribute</code>
               and <code>@ApplicationException</code>.
            </para>
         </warning>
         <note>
            <para>
               <code>TransactionAttributeType.REQUIRES_NEW</code> and
               <code>TransactionAttributeType.NOT_SUPPORTED</code> are not yet supported on managed
               beans. This will be added before seam-persistence goes final.
            </para>
         </note>
         <para>
            Lets have a look at some code. Annotations applied at a method level override annotations
            applied at the class level. 
         </para>
         <programlisting role="JAVA">@TransactionAttribute /*Defaults to TransactionAttributeType.REQUIRED */
class TransactionaBean
{

   /* This is a transactional method, when this method is called a transaction
    * will be started if one does not already exist.
    * This behavior is inherited from the @TransactionAttribute annotation on
    * the class.
    */
    void doWork()
    {
      ...
    }
    
    /* This a transaction will not be started for this method, however it */
    /* will not complain if there is an existing transaction active.      */
    @TransactionAttributeType(TransactionAttributeType.SUPPORTED)
    void doMoreWork()
    {
      ...
    }
    
    /* This method will throw an exception if there is no transaction active when */
    /* it is invoked.                                                             */
     
    @TransactionAttributeType(TransactionAttributeType.MANDATORY)
    void doEvenMoreWork()
    {
      ...
    }  
    
    /* This method will throw an exception if there is a transaction active when */
    /* it is invoked.                                                            */
    @TransactionAttributeType(TransactionAttributeType.NOT_SUPPORTED)
    void doOtherWork()
    {
      ...
    }
}         </programlisting>
      </section>
   
   </section>

   <section id="persistence.seam-managed-persistence-contexts">
      <title>Seam-managed persistence contexts</title>

      <para>
         If you're using Seam outside of a Java EE environment, you can't rely upon the
         container to manage the persistence context lifecycle for you. Even if you are
         in an EE environment, you might have a complex application with many loosely
         coupled components that collaborate together in the scope of a single conversation,
         and in this case you might find that propagation of the persistence context between
         component is tricky and error-prone.
      </para>
        
      <para>
         In either case, you'll need to use a <emphasis>managed persistence context</emphasis> 
         (for JPA) or a <emphasis>managed session</emphasis> (for Hibernate) in your components.
         A Seam-managed persistence context is just a built-in Seam component that manages an
         instance of <literal>EntityManager</literal> or <literal>Session</literal> in the
         conversation (or any other) context. You can inject it with <literal>@In</literal>.
      </para>
        
      <section>
         <title>Using a Seam-managed persistence context with JPA</title>
           
         <programlisting role="java">@SeamManaged
@Produces
@PersistenceUnit
@ConversationScoped
EntityManagerFactory producerField;
         </programlisting>
         <para>
            This is just an ordinary resource producer field as defined by the CDI 
            specification, however the presence of the <literal>@SeamManaged</literal>
            annotation tells seam to create a seam managed persistence context from 
            this <literal>EntityManagerFactory</literal>. This managed
            persistence context can be injected normally, and has the same scope and 
            qualifiers that are specified on the resource producer field.
         </para>
         <para>
            This will work even in a SE environment where <code>@PersistenceUnit</code>
            injection is not normally supported. This is because the seam persistence 
            extensions will bootstrap the <code>EntityManagerFactory</code> for you.
         </para>
         
         <para>
            Now we can have our <literal>EntityManager</literal> injected using:
         </para>
   
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject EntityManager entityManager;]]></programlisting>
     
         <note>
            <para>
               The more eagle eyed among you may have noticed that the resource producer 
               field appears to be conversation scoped, which the CDI specification does 
               not require containers to support. This is actually not the case, as the 
               @ConversationScoped annotation is removed by the seam persistence portable 
               extension. It only specifies the scope of the created SMPC, not the 
               EntityManagerFactory.
            </para>
         </note>
     
         <warning>
            <para>
               If you are using EJB3 and mark your class or method 
               <literal>@TransactionAttribute(REQUIRES_NEW)</literal> then the 
               transaction and persistence context shouldn't be propagated to method
               calls on this object.  However as the Seam-managed persistence
               context is propagated to any component within the conversation, it
               will be propagated to methods marked <literal>REQUIRES_NEW</literal>.
               Therefore, if you mark a method <literal>REQUIRES_NEW</literal> then
               you should access the entity manager using @PersistenceContext.
            </para>
         </warning>
          
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Seam-managed persistence contexts and atomic conversations</title>
         <para>
            Persistence contexts scoped to the conversation allows you to program optimistic 
            transactions that span multiple requests to the server without the need to use the 
            <literal>merge()</literal> operation , without the need to re-load 
            data at the beginning of each request, and without the need to wrestle with the 
            <literal>LazyInitializationException</literal> or 
            <literal>NonUniqueObjectException</literal>.
         </para>
     
         <para>
            As with any optimistic transaction management, transaction isolation and consistency
            can be achieved via use of optimistic locking. Fortunately, both Hibernate and EJB 
            3.1 make it very easy to use optimistic locking, by providing the 
            <literal>@Version</literal> annotation.
         </para>
     
         <para>
            By default, the persistence context is flushed (synchronized with the database)
            at the end of each transaction. This is sometimes the desired behavior. But very 
            often, we would prefer that all changes are held in memory and only written to
            the database when the conversation ends successfully. This allows for truly
            atomic conversations. Unfortunately there is currently no simple, usable and 
            portable way to implement atomic conversations using EJB 3.1 persistence. 
            However, Hibernate provides this feature as a vendor extension to the 
            <literal>FlushModeType</literal>s defined by the specification, and it is 
            our expectation that other vendors will soon provide a similar extension.
         </para>
     
         <para>
            Seam lets you specify <literal>FlushModeType.MANUAL</literal> when beginning a
            conversation. Currently, this works only when Hibernate is the underlying 
            persistence provider, but we plan to support other equivalent vendor extensions.
         </para>
     
         <para>
            TODO: The next section needs to be updated to seam 3.
         </para>
     
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject EntityManager em; //a Seam-managed persistence context
   
   @Begin(flushMode=MANUAL)
   public void beginClaimWizard() {
       claim = em.find(Claim.class, claimId);
   }]]></programlisting>
   
         <para>
            Now, the <literal>claim</literal> object remains managed by the persistence context
            for the rest of the conversation. We can make changes to the claim:
         </para>
   
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public void addPartyToClaim() {
       Party party = ....;
       claim.addParty(party);
   }]]></programlisting>
   
         <para>
            But these changes will not be flushed to the database until we explicitly force
            the flush to occur:
         </para>
   
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@End
   public void commitClaim() {
       em.flush();
   }]]></programlisting>
   
         <para>
            Of course, you could set the <literal>flushMode</literal> to <literal>MANUAL</literal>
            from pages.xml, for example in a navigation rule:
         </para>
   
         <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<begin-conversation flush-mode="MANUAL" />]]></programlisting>
         
         <para>
            You can set any Seam Managed Persistence Context to use manual flush
            mode:
         </para>
         
         <programlisting><![CDATA[<components xmlns="http://jboss.com/products/seam/components"
            xmlns:core="http://jboss.com/products/seam/core">
            <core:manager conversation-timeout="120000" default-flush-mode="manual" />
         </components>]]></programlisting>
         
      </section>
   
   
      <section>
         <title>Using EL in EJB-QL/HQL</title>
         <para>
             Seam proxies the <literal>EntityManager</literal> or <literal>Session</literal>
             object whenever you use a Seam-managed persistence context or inject a container
             managed persistence context using <literal>@PersistenceContext</literal>. This
             lets you use EL expressions in your query strings, safely and efficiently. For
             example, this:
         </para>
     
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[User user = em.createQuery("from User where username=#{user.username}")
   .getSingleResult();]]></programlisting>
   
         <para>is equivalent to:</para>
   
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[User user = em.createQuery("from User where username=:username")
   .setParameter("username", user.getUsername())
   .getSingleResult();]]></programlisting>
   
         <para>
            Of course, you should never, ever write it like this:
         </para>
   
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[User user = em.createQuery("from User where username=" + user.getUsername()) //BAD!
   .getSingleResult();]]></programlisting>
            
         <para>
            (It is inefficient and vulnerable to SQL injection attacks.)
         </para>
           
      </section>
       
      <section>
         <title>Setting up the EntityManager</title>
         
         <para>
           Sometimes you may want to perform some additional setup on the <code>EntityManager</code> after
           it has been created. For example, if you are using Hibernate you may want to set a filter. Seam
           persistence fires a <code>SeamManagedPersistenceContextCreated</code> event when a Seam managed
           persistence context is created. You can observe this event and perform any setup you require in
           an observer method. For example:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA">public void setupEntityManager(@Observes SeamManagedPersistenceContextCreated event) {
   Session session = (Session)event.getEntityManager().getDelegate();
   session.enableFilter("myfilter");     
}         
         </programlisting>         
      </section>
    
   </section>
    
</chapter>
