<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="persistence">
    <title>Seam Persistence Reference</title>

    <para>
        Seam provides extensive support for the two most popular persistence
        architectures for Java: Hibernate3, and the Java Persistence API
        introduced with EJB 3.0. Seam's unique state-management architecture
        allows the most sophisticated ORM integration of any web application
        framework.
    </para>
    
    <note>
      <para>
        Previously the Seam Persistence module provided transactional-related features also, however as
        transactions are not an exclusive feature of the persistence domain, these features have been 
        moved into a separate module called Seam Transactions.
      </para>
    </note>

    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>
            Seam grew out of the frustration of the Hibernate team with the
            statelessness typical of the previous generation of Java application
            architectures. The state management architecture of Seam was originally
            designed to solve problems relating to persistence &#8212; in particular
            problems associated with<emphasis>optimistic transaction processing</emphasis>.
            Scalable online applications always use optimistic transactions. An atomic
            (database/JTA) level transaction should not span a user interaction unless
            the application is designed to support only a very small number of concurrent
            clients. But almost all interesting work involves first displaying data
            to a user, and then, slightly later, updating the same data. So Hibernate was
            designed to support the idea of a persistence context which spanned an
            optimistic transaction.
        </para>

        <para>
            Unfortunately, the so-called "stateless" architectures that preceded Seam and
            EJB 3.0 had no construct for representing an optimistic transaction. So, instead,
            these architectures provided persistence contexts scoped to the atomic
            transaction. Of course, this resulted in many problems for users, and is the
            cause of the number one user complaint about Hibernate: the dreaded
            <literal>LazyInitializationException</literal>. What we need is a construct
            for representing an optimistic transaction in the application tier.
        </para>

        <para>
            EJB 3.0 recognizes this problem, and introduces the idea of a stateful
            component (a stateful session bean) with an <emphasis>extended persistence context</emphasis>
            scoped to the lifetime of the component. This is a partial solution to the problem (and is a 
            useful construct in and of itself) however there are two problems:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The lifecycle of the stateful session bean must be managed manually
                    via code in the web tier (it turns out that this is a subtle problem
                    and much more difficult in practice than it sounds).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Propagation of the persistence context between stateful components
                    in the same optimistic transaction is possible, but tricky.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            Seam solves the first problem by providing conversations, and stateful
            session bean components scoped to the conversation. (Most conversations
            actually represent optimistic transactions in the data layer.) This is
            sufficient for many simple applications (such as the Seam booking
            demo) where persistence context propagation is not needed. For more
            complex applications, with many loosely-interacting components in each
            conversation, propagation of the persistence context across components
            becomes an important issue. So Seam extends the persistence context
            management model of EJB 3.0, to provide conversation-scoped extended
            persistence contexts.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Getting Started</title>

        <para>
            To get started with Seam Persistence you need to add <literal>seam-persistence.jar</literal>
            and <literal>solder-impl.jar</literal> to your deployment.  The relevant Maven configuration 
            is as follows:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.seam.persistence</groupId>
  <artifactId>seam-persistence-api</artifactId>
  <version>${seam.persistence.version}</version>
</dependency>

<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.seam.persistence</groupId>
  <artifactId>seam-persistence</artifactId>
  <version>${seam.persistence.version}</version>
</dependency>

<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.solder</groupId>
  <artifactId>solder-impl</artifactId>
  <version>${solder.version}</version>
</dependency>
]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            You will also need to have a JPA provider on the classpath. If you are
            using java EE this is taken care of for you. If not, we recommend hibernate.
        </para>

        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupId>org.hibernate</groupId>
  <artifactId>hibernate-core</artifactId>
  <version>3.5.1-Final</version>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section id="persistence.seam-managed-persistence-contexts">
        <title>Seam-managed persistence contexts</title>

        <para>
            If you're using Seam outside of a Java EE environment, you can't rely upon the
            container to manage the persistence context lifecycle for you. Even if you are
            in an EE environment, you might have a complex application with many loosely
            coupled components that collaborate together in the scope of a single conversation,
            and in this case you might find that propagation of the persistence context between
            component is tricky and error-prone.
        </para>

        <para>
            In either case, you'll need to use a
            <emphasis>managed persistence context</emphasis>
            (for JPA) or a
            <emphasis>managed session</emphasis>
            (for Hibernate) in your components.
            A Seam-managed persistence context is just a built-in Seam component that manages an
            instance of
            <literal>EntityManager</literal>
            or
            <literal>Session</literal>
            in the
            conversation (or any other) context. You can inject it with<literal>@Inject</literal>.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Using a Seam-managed persistence context with JPA</title>

            <programlisting role="java">@ExtensionManaged
@Produces
@PersistenceUnit
@ConversationScoped
EntityManagerFactory producerField;</programlisting>

            <para>
                This is just an ordinary resource producer field as defined by the CDI
                specification, however the presence of the
                <literal>@ExtensionManaged</literal>
                annotation tells seam to create a seam managed persistence context from
                this<literal>EntityManagerFactory</literal>. This managed
                persistence context can be injected normally, and has the same scope and
                qualifiers that are specified on the resource producer field.
            </para>

            <para>
                This will work even in a SE environment where
                <code>@PersistenceUnit</code>
                injection is not normally supported. This is because the seam persistence
                extensions will bootstrap the
                <code>EntityManagerFactory</code>
                for you.
            </para>

            <para>
                Now we can have our <literal>EntityManager</literal> injected using:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject EntityManager entityManager;]]></programlisting>

            <note>
                <para>
                    The more eagle eyed among you may have noticed that the resource producer
                    field appears to be conversation scoped, which the CDI specification does
                    not require containers to support. This is actually not the case, as the
                    <literal>@ConversationScoped</literal> annotation is removed by the Seam Persistence portable
                    extension. It only specifies the scope of the created SMPC, not the
                    <code>EntityManagerFactory</code>.
                </para>
            </note>

            <warning>
                <para>
                    If you are using EJB3 and mark your class or method <literal>@TransactionAttribute(REQUIRES_NEW)</literal>
                    then the transaction and persistence context shouldn't be propagated to method
                    calls on this object. However as the Seam-managed persistence
                    context is propagated to any component within the conversation, it
                    will be propagated to methods marked <literal>REQUIRES_NEW</literal>.
                    Therefore, if you mark a method <literal>REQUIRES_NEW</literal>
                    then you should access the entity manager using <literal>@PersistenceContext</literal>.
                </para>
            </warning>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Seam-managed persistence contexts and atomic conversations</title>
            <para>
                Persistence contexts scoped to the conversation allows you to program optimistic
                transactions that span multiple requests to the server without the need to use the
                <code>merge()</code> operation , without the need to re-load
                data at the beginning of each request, and without the need to wrestle with the
                <code>LazyInitializationException</code> or <code>NonUniqueObjectException</code>.
            </para>

            <para>
                As with any optimistic transaction management, transaction isolation and consistency
                can be achieved via use of optimistic locking. Fortunately, both Hibernate and EJB
                3.1 make it very easy to use optimistic locking, by providing the
                <literal>@Version</literal> annotation.
            </para>

            <para>
                By default, the persistence context is flushed (synchronized with the database)
                at the end of each transaction. This is sometimes the desired behavior. But very
                often, we would prefer that all changes are held in memory and only written to
                the database when the conversation ends successfully. This allows for truly
                atomic conversations. Unfortunately there is currently no simple, usable and
                portable way to implement atomic conversations using EJB 3.1 persistence.
                However, Hibernate provides this feature as a vendor extension to the
                <literal>FlushModeType</literal>s defined by the specification, and it is
                our expectation that other vendors will soon provide a similar extension.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Using EL in EJB-QL/HQL</title>
            <para>
                Seam proxies the <literal>EntityManager</literal> or <literal>Session</literal>
                object whenever you use a Seam-managed persistence context. This
                lets you use EL expressions in your query strings, safely and efficiently. For
                example, this:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[User user = em.createQuery("from User where username=#{user.username}")
   .getSingleResult();]]></programlisting>

            <para>is equivalent to:</para>

            <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[User user = em.createQuery("from User where username=:username")
   .setParameter("username", user.getUsername())
   .getSingleResult();]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Of course, you should never, ever write it like this:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[User user = em.createQuery("from User where username=" + user.getUsername()) //BAD!
   .getSingleResult();]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                (It is inefficient and vulnerable to SQL injection attacks.)
            </para>

            <warning>
                <para>
                  This only works with Seam managed persistence contexts, not persistence contexts that are injected
                  with <code>@PersistenceContext</code>.
                </para>
            </warning>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Setting up the EntityManager</title>

            <para>
                Sometimes you may want to perform some additional setup on the <code>EntityManager</code> after
                it has been created. For example, if you are using Hibernate you may want to set a filter. Seam
                persistence fires a
                <code>SeamManagedPersistenceContextCreated</code>
                event when a Seam managed
                persistence context is created. You can observe this event and perform any setup you require in
                an observer method. For example:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="JAVA">public void setupEntityManager(@Observes SeamManagedPersistenceContextCreated
                event) {
                Session session = (Session) event.getEntityManager().getDelegate();
                session.enableFilter("myfilter");
                }
            </programlisting>

        </section>

    </section>

</chapter>
